Irrelevant.
Very good. Okay so today's דף Daf ע"ד Ayin Daled we pick
up at the very bottom of ע"ג עמוד ב'. Ayin Gimel Amud
Bais. We are two dots.
רבי שמעון אומר מנחת חוטא של כהנים. Rabbi Shimon Omer Minchas Chotei
Shel Kohanim. So the question was, the תורה Torah says that when
a כהן Kohen brings a מנחה Mincha you fully burn it, you
don't and you don't do קמיצה Kmitza and you don't eat the
rest. But that's a standard מנחה Mincha which functions somewhat like an
עולה. Olah. What about if it's a מנחה Mincha for a sin,
where there is no logical parallel to burn the whole thing if
it's functioning as a type of a חטאת? Chatas? So nevertheless the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says you burn the whole thing. רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says you do the קמיצה Kmitza and you separate you
burn the קמיצה Kmitza separately and the rest of it separately. So
they both agree that you burn it all because it doesn't it's
not excluded from the category of a general מנחת כהן, Minchas Kohen,
but רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says because it's a מנחת חוטא Minchas
Chotei you still do a קמיצה. Kmitza. So let's take a look
at this. רבי שמעון אומר מנחת חוטא של כהנים. Rabbi Shimon Omer
Minchas Chotei Shel Kohanim. מנא הני מילי? Mena Hanei Mili? Where do
we get this from? דתנו רבנן Detanu Rabbanan our Rabbis taught: והיתה
לכהן כמנחה. V'hayisaho Lakohen Kamincha. It shall be for the כהן Kohen
like a מנחה. Mincha. This is what the תורה Torah says
after I even forgot the initial context, sorry, excuse me. I think
this is just
I think this is just by the standard מנחת חוטא, Minchas Chotei,
but let me just double check.
ויקרא ה' Vayikra Hei that would make sense if that's what it
is. So
okay,
yes so this is about if it's for a sin and it's
you're allowed to bring a מנחה Mincha for it. It's an עולה
ויורד. Olah V'Yored. ואם לא תשיג ידו לשתי תורים או לשני בני
יונה והביא את קרבנו אשר חטא עשירית האפה סלת לחטאת לא ישים
עליה שמן ולא יתן עליה לבונה כי חטאת היא. V'im Lo Sagia
Yado L'shtei Sorim O L'shnei Bnei Yona V'heivi Es Korbano Asher Chata
Asiris Haeifah Soles L'chatas Lo Yasim Aleha Shemen V'lo Yitein Aleha Levonah
Ki Chatas Hi.
And then at the end it says וכיפר עליו הכהן על חטאתו
אשר חטא מאחת מאלה ונסלח לו והיתה לכהן כמנחה. V'chiper Alav Hakohen
Al Chata'aso Asher Chata Me'achas Me'eleh V'nislach Lo V'hayisaho Lakohen Kamincha. So
even though this is functioning as a חטאת, Chatas, which is not
the normal role of a מנחה, Mincha, the תורה Torah says nevertheless
it is like a מנחה. Mincha. So what's that coming to tell
me? So let's take a look.
So the first thing it says is שתהא עבודה כשרה בו. Shetei
Avodah Kashera Bo. So to understand לכהן Lakohen that even if it's
the כהן's Kohen's own חטאת, Chatas, even if the כהן Kohen himself
had to bring it for his own sin, then it can then
it still functions like a normal מנחה, Mincha, so he is allowed
to do the עבודה Avodah for something that is for his own
sin. Alright, so that's a new idea. We haven't learned that before,
we'll get back to that. So then the ברייתא Beraisa goes on:
אתה אומר שתהא עבודה כשרה בו. Atah Omer Shetei Avodah Kashera Bo.
You're telling me that it's coming to teach that he can do
his own the עבודה Avodah for his own מנחת חוטא. Minchas Chotei.
או אינו אלא להתיר מנחת חוטא של כהנים. O Eino Ela L'hatir
Minchas Chotei Shel Kohanim.
Maybe what it's really telling me is is that he can eat
the מנחת חוטא. Minchas Chotei. Maybe it's telling me this here is
like a מנחה Mincha and again if we're going to assume, although
you know they're not clear in the פסוקים, Pesukim, but for whatever
reason we're going to assume that it's referred to a כהן's Kohen's
own מנחה Mincha that he's bringing for a sin, so maybe by
saying it's like a מנחה Mincha is coming to say it's like
a normal מנחה Mincha and that he can eat the remainder. So
maybe it's telling me that a מנחה Mincha that a כהן Kohen
brings for a sin functions like a normal מנחה Mincha and he
eats the remainder. או אינו אלא O Eino Ela maybe it's coming
להתיר מנחת חוטא של כהנים L'hatir Minchas Chotei Shel Kohanim
to allow him to eat the remainder of a sin מנחה Mincha
for כהנים. Kohanim. ומה אני מקיים וכל מנחת כהן כליל תהיה לא
תאכל? Uma Ani Mekayeim V'kol Minchas Kohen Kalil Tihyeh Lo Seiachel?
So what do I do at the פסוק Pasuk that says every
מנחה Mincha of a כהן Kohen should fully be burned it should
not be eaten? If I'm going to suggest that here maybe you
are allowed to eat it. So maybe that's במנחת נדבתו, B'minchas Nedavaso,
maybe that's his free-will מנחה. Mincha. אבל חובתו Aval Chovaso an obligatory
מנחה Mincha like this for a sin תאכל Tei'achel
maybe it should be eaten. So maybe you read this פסוק Pasuk
that talks about the מנחת חוטא. Minchas Chotei. Number one, we are
assuming it's talking about one that a כהן Kohen himself is bringing
for whatever reason because and number two maybe because of the לכהן.
Lakohen. And number two, the כמנחה Kamincha at the end, maybe that's
coming to tell me that he treats it like a normal ישראל's
Yisrael's מנחה Mincha and he gets to eat the remainder. How do
I know that's not true? So תלמוד לומר Talmud Lomar because I
know from another פסוק. Pasuk.
I'm sorry,
no, because I know from this פסוק: Pasuk: תלמוד לומר והיתה לכהן
כמנחה. Talmud Lomar V'hayisaho Lakohen Kamincha. No, because the emphasis of כמנחה
Kamincha I'm going to read the following way. Meaning if I just
said והיתה לכהן, V'hayisaho Lakohen, maybe I would have read it that
he gets to keep it, he gets to eat it. But because
it ends by not just saying לכהן Lakohen he gets it, but
it says כמנחה Kamincha like a מנחה, Mincha, so it means I
have to compare it to a standard מנחה. Mincha. But what standard
מנחה? Mincha? His standard מנחה. Mincha. מקיש חובתו לנדבתו. Makish Chovaso L'nedavaso.
His obligatory to his to his free-will מנחה. Mincha. מה נדבתו אינה
נאכלת Mah Nedavaso Einah Ne'echeles
the same way a free-will מנחה Mincha of a כהן Kohen is
not eaten it's fully burned, אף חובתו אינה נאכלת Af Chovaso Einah
Ne'echeles
even his obligatory is not burned. So it's a little complicated because
it's doing a lot of things from the פסוק Pasuk but basically
it's saying like this. Number one we're assuming the פסוק Pasuk is
talking about a מנחה Mincha that the כהן Kohen brings for a
sin. Number two we're going to assume the last word כמנחה, Kamincha,
although you know... it could mean which type of מנחה, mincha, ישראל'ס
Yisrael's מנחה, mincha, his מנחה, mincha, we're going to assume it means
like a normal מנחה mincha he would bring, a free will מנחה,
mincha, which means it gets fully burned. So from there I learn
that a מנחת חוטא minchas chotei that a כהן kohen brings gets
fully burned. So then what do I do with the first word
לכהן? lakohen? לכהן lakohen seems to be giving him some special rights
to it. What rights is it giving to him? It's giving him
the right in order to be מקריב makriv it. So even though
it's his own מנחת חוטא, minchas chotei, which we're going to assume,
then the לכהן lakohen says he has rights to be מקריב makriv
it. And the כמנחה kamincha is saying, but it functions like a
normal מנחה mincha of his, which is fully burned. That's the first
way it's being read. אמר רבי שמעון, amar Rebbe Shimon, רבי שמעון
Rebbe Shimon says back,
וכי נאמר והיה לכהן כמנחתו, vechi ne'emar vehaya lakohen kaminchaso, does it
say it's like the כהן kohen like his מנחה, mincha, which would
force you to compare it to a מנחת נדבה minchas nedava that's
fully burned? והלא לא נאמר אלא כמנחה, vehallo lo ne'emar ella kamincha,
like a standard מנחה. mincha. אלא, ella, here's how you read the
פסוק. pasuk. להקיש מנחת חוטא של כהנים כמנחת חוטא lehakish minchas chotei
shel kohanim kaminchas chotei what? 94 עמוד א. Amud Aleph.
Oh, did I knock it? עין דלת עמוד א? Ayin-Dalet Amud Aleph?
I did. I'm sorry. I only forget to, let's, anyway. מנחת חוטא
של כהנים כמנחת חוטא של ישראל, minchas chotei shel kohanim kaminchas chotei
shel Yisrael, to connect it to the מנחת חוטא minchas chotei of
a ישראל. Yisrael. So not like I was originally reading it. I
was jumping ahead. So therefore it's like a כהן, kohen, like a
מנחה, mincha, like a normal מנחה mincha of a ישראל. Yisrael. Now,
Rebbe Shimon is not going to go so far to say that
the כהן kohen gets to eat it. Nobody suggests that because you
have this very general פסוק pasuk that says every מנחה mincha of
a כהן kohen is fully burned. But at least it's like a
מנחת חוטא minchas chotei of a ישראל Yisrael to tell you that
you do a קמיצה kmitza and you separate the קמיצה kmitza from
the rest. So at the end, although there's other things going around
here, לבריאות, gesundheit, the core is on this פסוק pasuk that speaks
about a מנחת חוטא, minchas chotei, that both Rebbe Shimon and the
חכמים Chachamim agree we're going to assume it's talking about a מנחת
חוטא minchas chotei of a כהן. kohen. And the question is how
do you read the פסוק pasuk כמנחה? kamincha? Does it mean like
a כהן'ס kohen's normal מנחה, mincha, which is fully burned as one
unit? Or does it mean כמנחה kamincha like a מנחת חוטא minchas
chotei of a ישראל, Yisrael, which is what Rebbe Shimon says, which
is that it is, that it is, a קמיצה kmitza is burned
separate from the rest? It's true we will burn the rest, we'll
talk about that in a minute, but first we start with the
idea like a מנחת חוטא minchas chotei of a ישראל, Yisrael, that
at least the קמיצה kmitza is taken and burned. Two questions. Okay,
let's finish the idea and then you'll get your questions. Okay. מה
מנחת חוטא של ישראל נקמצת, mah minchas chotei shel Yisrael nikmetzes, the
same way by a מנחת חוטא minchas chotei of ישראל Yisrael you
do קמיצה, kmitza,
אף מנחת חוטא של כהנים נקמצת. af minchas chotei shel kohanim nikmetzes.
The same will be true about this מנחה mincha that a כהן
kohen is bringing for a חטא. cheit. אי מה מנחת חוטא של
ישראל נקמצת ושיריה נאכלין, ei mah minchas chotei shel Yisrael nikmetzes veshireiha
ne'echalin, maybe we'll make the full equation, right? See, all good things
come to those who wait. Maybe we should make the equation complete,
that the same way a מנחת חוטא minchas chotei you do קמיצה
kmitza and you eat the rest, אף מנחת חוטא של כהנים נקמצת
ושיריה נאכלין? af minchas chotei shel kohanim nikmetzes veshireiha ne'echalin? So maybe
a מנחת חוטא minchas chotei of a כהנים kohanim you do קמיצה
kmitza and then you eat the rest? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, so
it says, לכהן כמנחה. lakohen kamincha. It will be for the כהן
kohen like a מנחה. mincha. לכהן כמנחה, lakohen kamincha, the כהן kohen
treats it as a normal מנחה mincha of a חוטא, chotei, which
means he does a קמיצה. kmitza. So in terms of his עבודה,
avoda, the עבודה avoda of a קמיצה, kmitza, that he does the
same way he would do like a normal מנחת חוטא. minchas chotei.
But ולא לאישים כמנחה, velo le'ishim kamincha, as far as the fire
is concerned, it's not like the normal מנחה mincha of a, you
know, of a what, it's not like the normal מנחת חוטא minchas
chotei of a ישראל. Yisrael. As far as the fire's concerned, the
fire gets everything. Wait, I don't get that. I don't get the...
So from the כהן'ס kohen's perspective, he treats it like he would
a מנחה, mincha, which is he does a קמיצה. kmitza. But as
far as the fire is concerned, the fire says don't give me
your למדנות, lamdus, I'm not treating it like a special
מנחה, mincha, as a normal מנחה, mincha, I'm treating it as, and
therefore as far as the fire's concerned, it's like a normal מנחת
כהן, minchas kohen, which it all gets burned. Okay, it's a whatever,
it's not the greatest דרשה, drasha, but anyway, it sort of reminds
me of the Yiddish joke or whatever, which I don't know how
to say the punchline in Yiddish, but anyway, you know, this guy
makes a lot of money, goes he buys himself a yacht and
he gets himself dressed up in his sailor suit and he invites
his mother on the yacht and he shows her all around. So
he says, so ma, what do you think? So she says, ביי
מיר דו ביסט א קאפיטאן, אבער ביי א קאפיטאן דו ביסט נישט
קיין קאפיטאן. By mir du bist a kapitan, aber by a kapitan
du bist nisht kein kapitan.
So for the כהן kohen it's כמנחה, kamincha, for the אישים ishim
it's not like a מנחה. mincha. Okay, anyway. So for the כהן
kohen gets to, so the כהן kohen does the קמיצה, kmitza, like
that way it's like the normal מנחה mincha of a ישראל, Yisrael,
but for the fire it's not like a מנחה mincha of ישראל.
Yisrael. For the fire it all gets burned. Okay, yes, Michael. Obviously,
it's, you can't get that all out of the פסוק. pasuk. It's
coming with an assumption that we're not going to violate the umbrella
rule that every מנחה mincha of a כהן kohen gets fully burned.
So if we're going to learn something from this פסוק pasuk like
it's like a normal מנחה, mincha, the only will be enough like
a normal מנחה mincha that you'll do a קמיצה, kmitza, but we're
still not going to violate the general rule that everything gets burned.
Okay, so that's basically the question, how do you read the כמנחה?
kamincha? Like a normal מנחה mincha of a כהן kohen or like
a מנחת ישראל minchas Yisrael at least to the fact that you
do a קמיצה? kmitza? Yes, Michael, what other question?
I just in general, I just wanted to know, do we ever
פסקן pasken like Rebbe Shimon in anything?
I don't know, I don't remember off
the top of my head, right?
Not like, not against חבירו chaveiro or חביריו, chaveirav, but yeah, I
think you need a real exception to rule like him, or you
know, a סתם stam like, as a general rule you wouldn't rule
like him, that's correct. So, okay, anyway, so although it is worth
noting as today's
ל"ג בעומר Lag B'Omer that this Rebbe Shimon is... for anybody who
wants to find any significance in that and you can see some
significance
in this whole thing, I don't know. Although I was thinking, although
I really haven't developed this thought, you know, the famous story of
רבי שמעון Reb Shimon coming out of the cave, you know, the
whole point of רבי שמעון Reb Shimon is he's an extremist. It's
all or nothing for him, right? And then he comes out of
the cave and somebody he sees a simple Jew like getting the
הדסים Hadasim ready for שבת, Shabbos, זכור Zachor and שמור, Shamor, you
know, he learns a little bit. So I think it's interesting here
that, you know, here you have the כהנים, Kohanim, which it's all
to God, right, that's coming, that's their whole מנחה Mincha is fully
burnt and at least here you have a little moderation here against
the חכמים. Chachamim. No, you do a קמיצה, Kmitza, maybe you separate
it off. Anyway, I don't know, have to develop that idea. Okay,
anyway, that's my ל"ג בעומר Lag B'Omer תורה, Torah, וייטער. Weiter. So
all right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
הכיצד, Ha keitzad, or how is it that you have like to
the כהן Cohen it's like a מנחת ישראל Minchas Yisroel but not
to the fire? קומץ קרב בעצמו Kometz karev b'atzmo ושיריים v'shirayim קרב
בעצמו kreiv b'atzmo ושיריים v'shir-
ושיריים v'shirayim קרבים בעצמן. kreivim b'atzman. You you burn them separately, you
do the קמיצה kmitza but they both get burnt. השתא עבודה כשירה
בו... Hashata avoda ksheira bo... so now that's... okay, that's what we
learned out. But again, let's not forget that that's what we learned
out from the word כמנחה. ka'mincha. We learned out from the word
לכהן l'kohen that the כהן Cohen has the right to be מקריב
makriv his מנחה, Mincha, מנחת חוטא Minchas chotei if he wants. So
now the גמרא Gemara says המהכא נפקא? ha'mei'hacha nafka? והשתא עבודתו
כשירה
בו מהכא נפקא? Ve'hashata avodaso ksheira bo mei'hacha nafka? This concept that
a כהן Cohen can opt to do his own עבודה, avoda, do
we learn it out from here, from the לכהן? l'kohen? המהכא נפקא?
Mei'hacha nafka? We learn it from another place. Where do we know
this? A ברייתא. Braisa. מניין לכהן שבא ומקריב קרבנותיו בכל עת ובכל
שעה שירצה? Minayin l'kohen she'ba u'makriv korbonosav b'chol eis u'v'chol sha'ah she'yirtzeh?
How do I know a כהן Cohen has an option to bring
his own personal קרבנות korbonot and be מקריב makriv them himself? That's
what we discussed yesterday, right, there was a rotation on שבת, Shabbos,
you know, every week a different family would serve.
And and then within the week a different day every every, you
know, you know, every sub-family would serve. But nevertheless, if you're bringing
your own קרבנות korbonot and you're a כהן, Cohen, you always have
the option of being מקריב makriv your own קרבנות. korbonot. How do
we know that's true?
תלמוד לומר ובא בכל אות נפשו ושרת Talmud lomar u'ba b'chol avas
nafsho v'sheireis and he shall serve. So that's a פסוק Pasuk in
דברים Devarim which talks about the idea of the rotation of the
כהנים Kohanim and speaks that a כהן Cohen can come whenever he
wants and serve. So you see, there you get, there we learn
that from. Why do you need it from here, from the מנחה?
Mincha? So here's what it says. אם מהתם, Im mei'hasam, if it
were from there, הוה אמינא hava amina I would have thought הני
מילי דבר שאין בא על חטא. hanei milei davar she'ein ba al
cheit. That's when it's not sin-related. That's when it's like just a
free-will sacrifice. אבל דבר שבא על חטא, Aval davar sheba al cheit,
if it's a if it's a sin-related קרבן, korbon, אימא לא, eima
lo, maybe you can't bring for yourself. Now I'll tell you why
this makes a lot of sense to me, and then you'll tell
me why you thought the opposite. To me it makes a lot
of sense for two reasons. Number one is if you're not bringing
it as a free will, you're more like less in control. You're
doing because you have to. If I'm opting to give a קרבן,
korban, I'm more in control, whatever, and then maybe I can also
have the right to do it the way I want. Number one.
Number two, more significantly, if it's coming for sin, you normally need
somebody else to atone for you. The whole idea of, you know,
you atoning for yourself, I mean, I guess in some ways, you
know, that's something that's wonderful about Judaism is that you don't need,
you know, is that you do your own תשובה, teshuvah, you do,
you know, atone for yourself. But at least in terms of ritual,
you know, there's an idea of the person here, the כהן Cohen
doing the עבודה, avoda, coming to God and bringing and presenting it
for you. That, you know, I at least the way the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash is set up, you know, you're right, maybe in
terms of the way we sort of
ultimately move towards the idea towards תשובה, teshuvah, you know, maybe that
makes sense. But at least in the sort of בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash context, normally it's they are bringing atonement for you and if
any place that should be true for a כהן Cohen himself, I
think it's more like atonement when you're more sort of distant from
the מקדש Mikdash that maybe you need somebody else to be doing
it for you. So to me it makes a lot of sense.
Why do you think it doesn't make sense?
Well, I was going to ask you this question. Like if I,
a Jew, let's say
a non-כהן, non-Cohen, does
a sin which which obligates him in a חטאת? chatas? Right. Right.
Is he supposed to bring it right away? Or is he or
does he have an option? No, you can opt whenever you want
to bring it. Correct. Yeah. There's no עניין inyan of trying to
bring it as soon as? No. No.
I mean, yeah, but it's not like it's not it doesn't really
force him to do I mean, same way as in doing better
to do תשובה teshuvah sooner rather than later.
But so it's really
the same thing as a נדבה? nedava? So because נדבה nedava you
have like a couple, you know, you have שלש רגלים כסדרן.
shalosh regalim kisidran. Yeah, I don't know, I don't even think you're
over, that's a question if you're over בל תאחר bal t'acher by
a חטאת. chatas. I don't think so. It's a discussion in the
beginning of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah I'd have to double check. Okay,
so we're going, meaning like if there's an עניין inyan in bringing
it quicker then, you know, you'd think like you should bring it
whenever he wants, just do it quicker. No, no. There's certainly not
an עניין inyan of bringing it quick. I mean, obviously general, it's
always good to have תשובה teshuvah quicker, the כפרה kappara quicker, but
okay. But that's what I was thinking, like you should come quicker
as opposed to like a נדבה nedava where you have some time
because of שלש רגלים כסדרן shalosh regalim kisidran maybe. Yeah, I don't
think it really expresses itself. Okay, so anyway, okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says maybe therefore if it's about sin you do not have
the option of doing it for yourself.
So therefore you needed the פסוק Pasuk by the מנחת חוטא Minchas
chotei that even if it's sin-related...
אלא מעתה ela ma'ata עבודה שבחוץ avoda she-bachutz אימא לא? aima lo?
גמרא Gemara says הא נמי מהכא נפקא? ha nami mehacha nafka? Still
I'll ask as it's coming from that פסוק pasuk of a מנחה,
mincha, מהתם נפקא?
mehatam nafka? I learn it out from another פסוק. pasuk. וכיפר הכהן
על הנפש השוגגת בחטא בשגגה. v'chiper hakohen al hanefesh hashogeges b'chet bishgaga.
So it says that the כהן kohen shall atone for the soul
that sins, when it sins in error, and this is about being
again I forget which קרבן, korban, במדבר ט"ו. Bamidbar tet-vav. במדבר ט"ו
Bamidbar tet-vav is about the ordinary just about the it might be
about the עבודה זרה avoda zara קרבן. korban. I don't remember off
hand. Yeah, והנפש אשר תחטא בשגגה והקריב עז בת שנתה לחטאת. v'hanefesh
asher techeta bishgaga v'hikriv ez bas shnata l'chatas. וכיפר הכהן על הנפש
השוגגת בחטא בשגגה לפני ה' לכפר עליו ונסלח לו. v'chiper hakohen al
hanefesh hashogeges b'chet bishgaga lifnei Hashem l'chaper alav v'nislach lo. So what
special קרבן korban is this? So רש"י, Rashi, yeah, בעבודה זרה. ba'avoda
zara. So it's a little it's funny what it's doing there, but
at the end of שלח Shelach you have this special פרשה parsha
about being a certain type of a חטאת chatas and this is
the פסוק pasuk that has the כהן kohen shall atone for the
sin whose souls. So, בחטא בשגגה. b'chet bishgaga. So מלמד שהכהן מתכפר
melamed she-hakohen mitkaper says the ברייתא Baraisa על ידי עצמו. al yedei
atzmo. So it's reading that again for what similar to the way
it read by the מנחת חוטא, minchat choteh, בחטא בשגגה b'chet bishgaga
is referring to the כהן's kohen own sin, that even if it's
his own sin that has souls, he shall be he shall atone.
So he brings he can bring his own קרבן korban for himself,
his own חטאת chatas for himself. אי מההוא, I me-hahu, so you
see we get it from there. So גמרא Gemara says no, אי
מההוא, I me-hahu, if it was from there, הוה אמינא הני מילי
בשוגג. hava amina hani mili b'shogeg. That if you sinned בשוגג. b'shogeg.
So therefore okay, again this is why I think the idea is
like if you're the more of a sinner you are, the less
you should be the one approaching God in this bringing of the
קרבן. korban. So therefore if it's בשוגג b'shogeg maybe then you're at
least it was an error and you can bring your own קרבן.
korban. אבל במזיד Aval b'meizid maybe if it was a sin במזיד
b'meizid לא, lo, then I would think you're not entitled to bring
a קרבן. korban. Now most קרבנות korbanot are of course בשוגג, b'shogeg,
but remember the מנחת חוטא minchat choteh is part of the is
you know is only for קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh v'yored. There's
variable variable, you know, cost קרבן, korban, which is at the end
of פרשת ויקרא Parshat Vayikra and that's a set of different things,
טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tum'as mikdash v'kodashav, swearing on a שבועה shvua and
so on and some of those things are אפילו במזיד. afilu b'meizid.
Specifically if you take a שבועת עדות shvuas eidus במזיד b'meizid then
you even that is included in those in that קרבן עולה ויורד.
korban oleh v'yored. So there is a some קרבנות korbanot that could
be brought even במזיד, b'meizid, some exceptions, and one of them is
exactly this מנחת חוטא minchat choteh and the חידוש chiddush is that
even there the כהן kohen can bring his own קרבן. korban. Okay,
so אבל במזיד לא קא משמע לן. aval b'meizid lo ka mashma
lan. במזיד היכי משכחת לה? B'meizid heichi mashkachat lah? What's an idea
of how do you get an example of מזיד? meizid? בזדון שבועה.
B'zadon shvua. If he's a willful שבועת שקר shvuas sheker about עדות
eidus and so on, other things, that is the פרשה parsha at
the end of ויקרא Vayikra where you could bring a קרבן עולה
ויורד korban oleh v'yored for מזיד meizid and even there כהן kohen
can bring his own קרבן. korban. By the way you'll see the
little ד dalet by במזיד b'meizid that he actually cross out those
words. רש"י Rashi did not have those words. It seems to have
been a later gloss. אבל במזיד לא קא משמע לן Aval b'meizid
lo ka mashma lan and then it went on. Somebody some later
editor said oh I in case you're wondering what's an example of
a מזיד meizid that brings a קרבן korban right and wrote in
those words זדון שבועה zadon shvua and then it got inserted into
the text. Okay so anyway but that would be an example. So
again I think that this is interesting and I think it's interesting
from the exact perspective of like the difference we think about if
you think about that contrast really between you know תשובה teshuva and
כפרה kapara the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. That besides that one is
more ritual based and the other is more you know sort of
like internal is the issue of the of the need of an
of an intercessor. The whole idea of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
is the fact that you need a כהנים kohanim you need the
ritual and you need כהנים kohanim while with תשובה teshuva you're just
supposed to do it yourself. So it is interesting here that when
it comes to the כהנים kohanim themselves it's sort of saying that
it's saying you know not to keep them out, allowing them to
do it themselves which I could see as somewhat sort of a
transition towards more of a תשובה teshuva mode that you don't need
even if you are the sinner you are allowed if you're כהן
kohen which in any way you have right to come in you're
allowed to come into the מקדש Mikdash and bring your own קרבן.
korban. So what so what do you think philosophically should be different
between a כהן kohen and a ישראל? Yisrael? Because they're already in
the פרשה parsha of doing עבודה. avoda. But that's more like that's
more like you know ritualistically. That's not more philosophically. I know it's
not more philosophically. Look in general there's the whole issue about how
to deal with the whole phenomenon of the מקדש Mikdash where they
are you know with all of the חטאת chatas and whatnot. The
idea of תשובה teshuva is very you know there's an idea of
וידוי viduy that's mentioned you know confessing the sins but actually a
type of a תשובה teshuva of transformation you know regret and you
know commitment or whatever that's very absent from the whole from all
of ויקרא. Vayikra. It's actually last week's פרשה parsha was the one
sense you have about you know והתוודו את עוונם ואת עוון אבותם
v'hisvadu es avonam v'es avon avosam right and it says you know
and it says there you have a slight sense of of a
not just being a ritual but a real change that's occurring but
it's pretty it's pretty rare so I don't have a good explanation.
I think that those are two different very different models and that
you know חז"ל Chazal were obviously living in a post-מקדש Mikdash model.
So it's always a question about whether they look to תשובה teshuva
as a second best. I do think that there's that's some of
what is going on here. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. תניא אידך. Tanya idach. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer,
so now we're back to what you do with a מנחה mincha
of a כהן, kohen, מנחת חוטא minchat chotei of a כהן. kohen.
Wait, so now we're saying that no matter what it is, no
matter, he can always bring מזיד? meizeid? If it's a קרבן korban
that you can bring מזיד, meizeid, a כהן kohen can bring it
for himself. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we taught another ברייתא. baraita. רבי
שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon omer: מנחת חוטא של כהנים נקמצת, minchat chotei
shel kohanim nikmetzet, so like we know, you take קמיצה kmitzah from
מנחת חוטא minchat chotei of a כהן, kohen, והקומץ קרב בפני עצמו,
ve-hakometz kareiv bifnei atzmo, you bring the קומץ kometz separately והשריים קרבים
בפני עצמם. vehashirayim kreivim bifnei atzmam. That we knew. רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון אומר, Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon omer, now רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
his son says: הקומץ קרב בעצמו והשריים מתפזרים על בית הדשן. hakometz
kareiv be-atzmo vehashirayim mitpazrim al beit hadeshen. That's how he deals with
it. You bring the קומץ, kometz, but you don't burn the remainder.
The remainder is not supposed to be burned. If you're taking a
קומץ, kometz, then the only thing you burn is the קומץ. kometz.
But what do you do with the remainder? You can't eat it
because it's a מנחת כהן. minchat kohen. מנחת כהן minchat kohen you
can't eat any part of it. You don't burn it because you
only burn a קומץ, kometz, you don't burn the rest. If you're
going to take a קומץ, kometz, you're only going to burn the
קומץ. kometz. So what do you do? You scatter it on the
בית הדשן, beit hadeshen, the place of ashes. Now the גמרא Gemara
says, what בית... beit... what בית הדשן? beit hadeshen? So let's take
a look. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא הוי בה רבי יוחנן. Amar
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba havie bah Rabbi Yochanan. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan was like questioning this. בית הדשן דהיכא? Beit hadeshen de-heicha? Which
בית הדשן? beit hadeshen? אי דלמעלה, I de-le-ma'ala, if it's the ash
pile on the top of the מזבח, mizbeiach, so that's where things
are actually burned, and then after they're burned the ashes are collected
at the top of the מזבח. mizbeiach. So היינו אבוה, hainu avuha,
then he's saying the same as his father. So say you burn
it on the ash pile. If you mean the ashes on the
מזבח, mizbeiach, you're basically saying you burn it on the מזבח. mizbeiach.
So you're saying what your father said. It doesn't sound that way.
אי דלמטה, I de-le-mata, if it's the בית הדשן beit hadeshen at
the floor of the מקדש, Mikdash, what does this mean? So רש''י
Rashi says it means that, you know, when they came down off
of the ramp they did תרומת הדשן trumat hadeshen in the morning,
they put the ashes at the side of the ramp. תוספות Tosafot
does not like that because the, you know, it says that the
ashes got absorbed there. Why would you call that a בית הדשן?
beit hadeshen? I don't know, it's still the place you put the
ashes. Anyway, תוספות Tosafot thinks it means the place in the עזרה
azarah that you burn the פרים הנשרפים ושעירים הנשרפים. parim hanisrafim ve-se'irim
hanisrafim. Right, when you do a קרבן korban where you bring the
blood into the... into the קודש, Kodesh, so you burn them, you
burn them somewhere in the עזרה. azarah. So there's another place there
where you burn. But whether רש''י Rashi or תוספות, Tosafot, the point
is it's not an act of הקרבה. hakrava. It's an act of,
you know, you have to destroy this thing. You don't have anything
to do with it, you burn it. Okay, so if that's what
you mean, יש לך דבר שקרב למטה? yesh lecha davar she-karev le-mata?
Do you have anything that לכתחילה lechat-chila you bring below, that you,
you know, if it's... how could it be that the way you...
what you do with it is לכתחילה lechat-chila to burn it? Now
again, I don't know exactly why that is so astounding because, you
know again, the פרים הנשרפים, parim hanisrafim, as תוספות Tosafot says it
makes an interesting parallel. Where there, you know, you do the blood
inside, the same way you do the קומץ kometz on the מזבח,
mizbeiach, you burn the innards on the מזבח mizbeiach for the פרים
הנשרפים, parim hanisrafim, but what do you do with the meat? You
don't eat it, you burn it. So here too, what do you
do with the שריים? shirayim? It's actually very parallel, right? It's the
remnant. What do you do with the remnant? There are times where
you don't eat the remnant, you actually destroy it, just like the
פרים הנשרפים. parim hanisrafim. So it's a little bit funny according to
תוספות, Tosafot, especially if that's what תוספות Tosafot thinks what the בית
הדשן beit hadeshen is, why that is so astounding for the גמרא.
Gemara. But anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara has. יש לך
דבר שקרב למטה? yesh lecha davar she-karev le-mata? Do you have anything
that begins by just being destroyed below? אמר ליה רבי אבא דילמא
הכי קאמר. Amar lei Rabbi Abba dilma hachi ko amar. I skipped
a line. No, you skipped a line. I'm not up to that.
אמר ליה רבי אבא, Amar lei Rabbi Abba, so רבי אבא Rabbi
Abba said: דילמא לאיבוד. dilma le-ibbud. So no, it maybe doesn't mean
that you do an act of הקרבה hakrava on the floor of
the מקדש. Mikdash. I actually was jumping to רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba.
Maybe it's not like you do an act of actually, you know,
offering it on the floor of the מקדש. Mikdash. Maybe לאיבוד. le-ibbud.
Maybe the point is you destroy it. You can't eat it, you
can't burn it on the מזבח, mizbeiach, so you destroy it. Maybe
that's the point. You understand what I mean? Wait, if you're going
to burn it on the floor of the מקדש, Mikdash, right, what's
the context in why you're burning? Are you burning it because it's
a type of a way of offering it to God? That's what
the גמרא Gemara says: יש לך הקרבה למטה? yesh lecha hakrava le-mata?
You don't do offerings on the floor of the מקדש. Mikdash. So
maybe it's a way of just destroying it. If it's... it's not
to be offered because it's not the קומץ. kometz. It's not to
be eaten because it's a מנחת כהנים. minchat kohanim. So what do
you do? You destroy it. So that's a pretty reasonable explanation. Is
that any different than just... it's the same thing, just conceptually. Yes,
but conceptually different. You're bothered how could you do a הקרבה? hakrava?
Don't call it a הקרבה. hakrava. Call it a destruction. Right? He's
just explaining what the logic of it is. And then what was
wrong with saying it's like פרים הנשרפים? parim hanisrafim? Nothing. I don't
know. That's a question I'm asking. אחיכו עליה. achichu alei. So they
laughed on him about... you know, they laughed at him. וכי יש
לך דבר שקרב לאיבוד? ve-chi yesh lecha davar she-karev le-ibbud? Or would
you... have anything that לכתחילה lechat-chila you would bring to be destroyed?
Now again, this is very strange because as I said, to me
פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim is a perfect parallel. You know, that you
bring it, you do זריקת הדם. zerikat hadam. What do you do
with the... you burn some of it. Here too, you burn the
קומץ. kometz. But what do you do with the meat? You destroy
the meat. So I don't know why they... why it's so astounding
for the גמרא. Gemara. sort of mocked this whole thing, seems like
a reasonable explanation. Anyway, תניא אבוה דרבי אבין, tanyei avuh d'Rebbi Avin,
but that is, that is the position of רבי אלעזר בר שמעון
Rebbi Elazar bar Shimon that it is burnt, the remainder is burnt
on the floor. תניא אבוה דרבי אבין, tanyei avuh d'Rebbi Avin, the
father of רבי אבין Rebbi Avin taught, כל מנחת כהן כליל תהיה
לא תאכל. kol minchas kohen kalil tihyeh lo se'achel. Every מנחה mincha
of a כהן. kohen. Now this is after the תורה Torah speaks
about this idea that you don't, that you burn an entire מנחה
mincha of a כהן. kohen. Comes in the תורה Torah after the
מנחת חביתין, minchas chavitin, after the מנחה mincha of a כהן גדול,
kohen gadol, half of which is burnt in the morning and half
in the afternoon. So it says like this, in צו, Tzav, וידבר
ה' אל משה לאמר זה קרבן אהרן ובניו אשר יקריבו לה' ביום
המשח אתו עשירית האיפה סלת מנחה תמיד מחציתה בבקר ומחציתה בערב. Vayidaber
Hashem el Moshe leimor zeh korban Aharon uvanav asher yakrivu l'Hashem beyom
himashach oso asiris ha-eifah soles mincha tamid machasitah vaboker umachasitah va'erev. So
half in the morning, half in the afternoon. It then says like
this, חוק עולם לה' כליל תקטר. chok olam l'Hashem kalil tuktar. Burn
it all, that's about the מנחת חביתין. minchas chavitin. And then after
it says burn it all, offer it all, it says, וכל מנחת
כהן כליל תהיה לא תאכל. v'chol minchas kohen kalil tihyeh lo se'achel.
Every מנחה mincha of a כהן kohen should be fully, should be
full, do not burn it. It doesn't say fully burnt, it says
should be כליל, kalil, should be complete, לא תאכל, lo se'achel, it
should not be eaten. Presumably the כליל kalil there means לא תאכל
lo se'achel burn it fully. Okay, but anyway that'll be important that
it doesn't actually use that verb. But anyway there you say don't
eat the מנחה mincha of any כהן, kohen, fully burn it. So
let's take a look. Okay, כל מנחת כהן כליל תהיה לא תאכל.
kol minchas kohen kalil tihyeh lo se'achel. לאכילה הקשתיה ולא לדבר אחר.
l'achila hikishtih v'lo l'davar acher. Now this is seemingly to defend רבי
אלעזר בר שמעון Rebbi Elazar bar Shimon and to explain how you
get this weird middle position that you don't burn it fully, but
you also don't, you don't burn it, but you don't eat it.
Because he says, look, the פסוק pasuk says every מנחה mincha of
a כהן kohen you cannot eat it. That's the basic rule. You
can't eat the remainder. But it doesn't say ולא לדבר אחר. v'lo
l'davar acher. It doesn't say that you either, that you burn it
fully. Notice it doesn't say כליל תקטר kalil tuktar in that פסוק.
pasuk. It just says כליל תהיה לא תאכל. kalil tihyeh lo se'achel.
So he's saying here's what רבי אלעזר בר שמעון, Rebbi Elazar bar
Shimon, here's sort of the position he's in. On the one hand,
he thinks you do a קמיצה kmitza based on that earlier פסוק
pasuk by מנחת חוטא, minchas chotei, that even a מנחת כהן minchas
kohen you do a קמיצה kmitza on. Now what's his options to
do with the remainder? Maybe eat it, but it says לא תאכל,
lo se'achel, you can't eat it. Maybe burn it, but no, it
doesn't say כליל תקטר, kalil tuktar, it just says לא תאכל. lo
se'achel. That's the rule. So it has, so therefore you don't burn
it, you don't eat it, all you're left with to do is
you destroy it on the floor of the מקדש. Mikdash. And that's
how he gets into that middle position. So what does the קמיצה
kmitza mean then? What? So what does the כליל kalil mean? Well
we'll see in a minute. Okay, so that's where he gets that
position. לאכילה הקשתיה ולא לדבר אחר. l'achila hikishtih v'lo l'davar acher. Just
not to be eaten, but not that you would burn it. So
מאי קאמר? mai ka'amar? What's he saying, which some understand means it
means like what do you do with the rest of the פסוק?
pasuk? So let's see. אמר אביי הכי קאמר. amar Abaye hachi ka'amar.
This is what he means. כל מנחת כהן, kol minchas kohen, here's
how he reads the פסוק. pasuk. כל מנחת כהן לא תאכל חובתו.
kol minchas kohen lo se'achel chovaso. If it's an obligatory מנחה, mincha,
like a מנחת חוטא, minchas chotei, then don't eat it. And then
what do you do? You burn the rest on the floor, but
you don't offer it up. כליל תהיה, kalil tihyeh, fully burn it,
what's that? נדבתו. nedavaso. If it's a free-will קרבן. korban. Okay, so
yes, he does use the word כליל kalil to say fully burn
it, but he understands that the תורה Torah is talking about two
different מנחות. menachos. רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos both say because look,
if all the תורה Torah wanted to say was fully burn it,
then why did it have to say לא תאכל? lo se'achel? Just
say fully burn it. If you're fully burning it, of course you're
not eating it. So it must be to tell you that there
are some that you fully burn and some that you don't burn
but you just don't eat. What do you fully burn? The מנחת
נדבה. minchas nedava. That you fully burn, it's sort of like an
עולה, olah, you fully burn it. The חוטא, מנחת חוטא chotei, minchas
chotei which is like a חטאת chatas which has a קמיצה, kmitza,
you don't fully burn it but you don't eat it and you
burn the remainder on the floor. That's רבי אלעזר בר שמעון. Rebbi
Elazar bar Shimon. Okay. So אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, so
רבא Rava said back to אביי, Abaye, סכינא חריפתא מפסקא קראי? sakina
charifa mafska krai? A sharp knife, you know, dividing the פסוק? pasuk?
How can you do that to the פסוק? pasuk? Say these two
words are talking about a מנחת חובה, minchas chova, these two words
are talking about a מנחת נדבה? minchas nedava? Doesn't the גמרא Gemara
do that all the time? I know, and the funny thing is,
not only does the גמרא Gemara do it all the time, רבא
Rava is about to do the exact same thing. So it's very
hard to understand what his question is. Let's see what his answer
is and you'll see it doesn't, it's hard to understand what his
question was. אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, rather רבא Rava said,
here's how you read the פסוק. pasuk. כל מנחת כהן כליל תהיה,
kol minchas kohen kalil tihyeh, every מנחה mincha of a כהן kohen
should be whole, complete, meaning fully burnt, נדבתו. nedavaso. If it's a
מנחת נדבה minchas nedava which again is like an עולה, olah, then
you fully burn it. לא תאכל, lo se'achel, don't eat it, but
also don't burn it, חובתו. chovaso. That's a מנחת חובה. minchas chova.
But it's exactly the same thing אביי Abaye did. The only thing
he did different is he explained the פסוק pasuk in order. אביי
Abaye explained it in reverse. אביי Abaye started by the end of
the פסוק pasuk and talking about the חובה chova and then worked
back to explain the נדבה. nedava. So in the end רבא'ס Rava's
question, רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos both say this because they have
nothing no other way to explain what's bothering רבא, Rava, is not
about how אביי Abaye explained the פסוק. pasuk. He explains the פסוק
pasuk the exact same way. He just says, don't, you know, you're
making it complicated by explaining the פסוק pasuk backwards. You should explain
the פסוק pasuk forwards. This is a very funny critique. Okay, but
either way they're both saying the same thing. They're saying burn it
fully is by a מנחת נדבה minchas nedava which is like an
עולה, olah, so you burn it fully. Don't eat it, but also
don't... Burn it fully is by the מנחת חוטא. minchas chotei. You
do the קמיצה. kemitza. What do you do with the rest? Don't
eat it, don't burn it, burn it on the floor. That's רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון's Rabbi Elazar b'Rei d'Rabbi Shimon position. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואיפוך אנא, v'eipoich ana, maybe I'll
reverse it? You know, I've been all along explaining that a מנחת
נדבה minchas nedava is like an עולה, olah, but here the גמרא
Gemara is asking that question. If you have to say one is
fully burnt and the other is not burnt but not eaten, how
do you know to say which one, you know, that it's the
מנחת נדבה minchas nedava that's fully burnt? Let's reverse it. So let's
say it's the מנחת חוטא minchas chotei that's fully burnt. So it
says no. מסתברא נדבתו הויא לריבויי. mistavra nedavaso hvei l'ribuyei. It makes
sense that the נדבה nedava is like the חביתין. chavitin. Remember in
the פסוקים, pesukim, what is the פסוק pasuk explicit about is fully
burnt? The מנחת חביתין minchas chavitin of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
So the question is which מנחה mincha is going to be most
similar to the מנחת חביתין minchas chavitin of the כהן גדול? Kohen
Gadol? The free-will מנחה mincha or the חטאת chatas מנחה? mincha? Now
you might say חטאת chatas because it's obligatory. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, I think free-will. Why? Because the חביתין chavitin is not
בא על החטא. ba al hachet. Ah, so okay, so that's a...
so okay, so let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara will make
a different, a certain group of comparisons. So the גמרא Gemara says
מסתברא mistavra makes sense, נדבתו הויא לריבויי, nedavaso hvei l'ribuyei, that the
free-will מנחה mincha is the one to compare to the חביתין, chavitin,
שכן, shekein, and here are the points of comparison. Wait, תדירה tadira
compared to חביתין chavitin and fully burnt, right? Fully burnt. שכן תדירה,
shekein tadira, they're constant. Now the חביתין chavitin is every day and
a נדבה nedava is not necessarily every day, but it could be
every day. A נדבה nedava can come at any time. A מנחת
חוטא minchas chotei comes much more rarely. A נדבה nedava has the
potential of coming at all times. לא חטי, lo choti, which is
what Michael said, that neither of which are coming for חטא. chet.
בסים ריחיה, basim reichei, and it has a pleasing odor. Now what
does that mean? It could mean physically and it could mean sort
of הלכתית. halachically. Physically is that both of them have oil in
it. A מנחת חוטא minchas chotei has no oil. So it doesn't
smell nice when you burn it the same way these other things
smell nice when you burn them, okay, which is another way of
saying that, you know, it's funny that it frames it as a
nice smell. Why doesn't it just say שכן שמן, shekein shemen, right,
they both have oil and מנחת חוטא minchas chotei doesn't? The other
thing that רש״י Rashi points out is is that by מנחת חוטא
minchas chotei and a מנחת חביתין, minchas chavitin, by a normal מנחה
mincha and a מנחת חביתין, minchas chavitin, it uses the phrase ריח
ניחוח. reiach nichoach. It never uses the phrase ריח ניחוח reiach nichoach
by מנחת חוטא, minchas chotei, which presumably is not only the fact
that it doesn't have oil, but it's also the fact that it's
because of that sin. It's not considered to be ריח ניחוח. reiach
nichoach. It's not coming, you know, it's not sort of framed as
much as a positive as much as a necessary. Okay, so those
are the ways that it's similar and therefore should be fully burnt.
So the גמרא Gemara says אדרבה, aderaba, maybe actually the opposite? חובתו
הויא לריבויי. chovaso hvei l'ribuyei. We should have said an obligatory מנחה
mincha was like a מנחת חביתין, minchas chavitin, meaning a מנחת חוטא
minchas chotei is like a מנחת חביתין. minchas chavitin. Maybe burn the
whole thing. Why? שכן, shekein, because behold, עשרון. isaron. First of all
they're both limited to an עשרון isaron of flour whereas a מנחת
נדבה minchas nedava you can bring as big as you want. חובה,
chovah, and they're both obligatory. The גמרא Gemara says nevertheless, הני נפישן,
hanei nefishan, the other points were greater points of comparison, there were
three versus two, and therefore we're going to assume that it's the
free-will מנחה mincha that you do fully and the מנחת חוטא minchas
chotei you not. Now remember this is all with רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Elazar b'Rei d'Rabbi Shimon. The
חכמים Chachamim hold that there's no difference. The חכמים Chachamim hold the
מנחת חוטא minchas chotei is just like a מנחת נדבה minchas nedava
and according to them they're both fully burnt. But of course the
more interesting positions are רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and his son because
they actually have it having this sort of middle space. So although
the גמרא Gemara says what's more similar to חביתין chavitin or not,
in my mind the comparison is much less about חביתין chavitin as
much more that a normal מנחה mincha is on the continuum of
an עולה. olah. And on the continuum of an עולה olah in
general you have to ask why is it that you don't burn
an entire מנחה? mincha? Why do you burn an entire, you know,
cow and a sheep and so on as an עולה olah and
you don't burn an entire מנחה? mincha? So whatever the reason for
that is, it's totally understandable that when it's a מנחת כהן minchas
Kohen you do burn it fully because it's like an עולה. olah.
A מנחת חוטא, minchas chotei, which is fundamentally like a חטאת, chatas,
which is fundamentally has a part that's not burnt, it makes sense
that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar
b'Rei d'Rabbi Shimon would say you have to treat the... you have
to do a קומץ kometz and do something different with the קומץ
kometz and the rest. And particularly interesting is רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rabbi Elazar b'Rei d'Rabbi Shimon that has the rest in this sort
of limbo status. You can't eat it, you can't offer it, you
burn it on the floor. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Rabbi, just let me make sure I understood what you
just said. You're saying that in some way the חכמים Chachamim make
sense because it's all framed in the concept of an עולה olah
and everything's to be burnt? No, that's how מנחת נדבה minchas nedava
makes sense to burn it fully. Actually I think that a מנחת
חוטא minchas chotei רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rabbi Elazar b'Rei d'Rabbi Shimon make more sense than the חכמים. Chachamim.
You know, a מנחת נדבה minchas nedava is a type of an
עולה olah the way I see it, or you know, loosely it's
whatever analogous to an עולה olah if you want to say it
like that and it makes sense to say, the question is really
why a מנחת ישראל minchas Yisrael you don't burn it fully if
anything. So there it makes sense, what... I wrote about it on
the blog, you'll read my blog more often you'll find out. My
short answer to that is is that I think it has to
do with the power of blood. I think that if you're doing
a קרבן korban of blood you don't have then you actually no
that's the opposite makes sense. Forget that. No, because then you would
have to דווקא davka do more by this. Can't remember what I
said. I'll have to think. Anyway, but whatever the reason is, it
makes sense that you do it fully, right? That if you're going
to do it fully, you do it fully in that type of
a מנחה. mincha. מנחת חוטא Minchas chotei which fundamentally paralleling the חטאת,
chatos, part is offered and part is eaten, it makes sense that
you're going to treat the half separately and therefore, and therefore רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon are a little more
persuasive. Okay, so let's take a look. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. ורבנן האי כל מנחת כהן כליל תהיה לא תאכל
מאי עביד ליה? Ve'rabbanan hai kol minchas kohen kalil tihyeh lo teachail
mai avid lei? What do they do with that פסוק pasuk since
they don't read the two halves to be talking about two different
types of מנחה? mincha? מבעי ליה לכדתניא Miba'u lei lachada tanya like
we taught in the ברייתא. baraita. אין לי אלא עליונה בכליל תקטיר
ותחתונה בלא תאכל. Ain li ela elyonah be-kalil taktir ve-tachtonah be-lo teachail.
And remember again the verbs used are when it talks about the
מנחת חביתין minchas chavitin it says burn it fully כליל תקטיר. kalil
taktir. When it talks about all מנחות minchos of כהן kohen it
just says don't eat. Although it says כליל kalil it doesn't say
burn it fully. So this is the question about so there's a
מצוה mitzvah to burn fully a מנחת כהן minchas kohen and there's
a negative מצוה mitzvah a לאו lav a negative prohibition to eat
a normal מנחת כהן. minchas kohen. How do you know to apply
the פסוקים pesukim to one to another? Okay. אין לי אלא עליונה
בכליל תקטיר. Ain li ela elyonah be-kalil taktir. I only know חביתין
chavitin you have a positive מצוה mitzvah to burn the whole thing.
ותחתונה Ve-tachtonah and the bottom case the normal מנחה mincha of a
כהן kohen בלא תאכל be-lo teachail a prohibition to eat. מנין ליתן
את האמור של זה בזה ואת האמור של זה בזה? Minayin liten
es ha'amur shel zeh be-zeh ve-es ha'amur shel zeh be-zeh? How do
I know to apply the פסוקים pesukim to one another? To say
there's a negative prohibition to eat from the מנחת חביתין minchas chavitin
and a positive מצוה mitzvah to burn fully all of the all
מנחות minchos of a כהן? kohen? תלמוד לומר כליל כליל לגזירה שוה.
Talmud lomar kalil kalil le-gezeirah shavah. It says כליל kalil in both
places. נאמר כאן כליל Ne'emar kan kalil it says here כליל kalil
it says כליל תקטיר kalil taktir ונאמר להלן כליל ve-ne'emar lalan kalil
and then it says כליל תהיה. kalil tihyeh. מה להלן בכליל תקטיר
אף כאן בכליל תקטיר. Mah lalan be-kalil taktir af kan be-kalil taktir.
The same way by מנחת חביתין minchas chavitin there's a מצוה mitzvah
to fully burn it then a normal מנחה mincha there's a מצוה
mitzvah to fully burn it of a כהן. kohen. ומה כאן ליתן
לא תעשה אכילתו אף להלן ליתן לא תעשה אכילתו. U'mah kan liten
lo sa'aseh achilaso af lalan liten lo sa'aseh achilaso. And the same
way by a normal מנחה mincha of a כהן kohen there's a
negative prohibition to eat it the same is true by מנחת חביתין.
minchas chavitin. So actually rather than רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbe Eliezer
bar Rebbe Shimon that uses the פסוק pasuk to tell you there
are different types of מנחות minchos for כהן kohen the חכמים Chachamim
use it to say the exact opposite to link the two and
to say all מנחות minchos of a כהן kohen are all the
same. There's a מצוה mitzvah to fully burn it, there's a prohibition
to eat it. Okay, just anyone explain why it doesn't say כליל
לאש kalil la'esh or something like that or just assume. What? Wait,
why does it say כליל לאש kalil la'esh or something like that?
What do you mean כליל תקטיר? kalil taktir? What do you כליל
תהיה, kalil tihyeh, yeah why doesn't it say to link the two?
No, it means why does it save you words? You don't have
to repeat the פסוק pasuk in both places, you do it through
a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. No when it says כליל תהיה kalil
tihyeh as opposed like I thought we were saying that כליל kalil
is sort of ambiguous, we don't know what כליל kalil means. No,
that's according to רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון. Rebbe Eliezer bar Rebbe Shimon.
No, we're using כליל kalil to just link the two. All right,
I don't know. We're using כליל kalil to link the two. Let's
finish this up. בעי רבינא כהן שאכל מן האימורים מהו? Ba'ei Ravina
kohen she-achal min ha-imurin mahu? Now we're going on to a different
point. From the כליל תקטיר kalil taktir or כליל תהיה לא תאכל
kalil tihyeh lo teachail we want to ask a question. Anything, this
idea that you fully burn it and you are not allowed to
eat it, is that limited to the מנחה mincha of a כהן?
kohen? What would be the story about anything else that's supposed to
be burned on the מזבח? mizbeach? Is there a negative prohibition to
eat things that are supposed to be burned on the מזבח? mizbeach?
Very reasonable question. Now תוספות Tosafos of course says this is bracketing
the question of מעילה. me'ilah. There might be מעילה me'ilah because it's
קדשים kodshim you're not supposed to benefit from קדשים. kodshim. But bracketing
that is there another prohibition about eating things that are supposed to
be burned that we can learn from this פסוק? pasuk? כליל תהיה
לא תאכל Kalil tihyeh lo teachail can that be telling us anything
that's supposed to be fully burned should not be eaten? So if
a כהן kohen eats the אימורים imurin מהו? mahu? What's the law?
But this is talking about a מנחה mincha so why would you
think it would apply? Because maybe the כליל תהיה לא תאכל kalil
tihyeh lo teachail can be taken out of context meaning anything that
כליל תהיה לא תאכל. kalil tihyeh lo teachail. I thought you don't
do that in זבחים. Zevachim. Does anyone have like it's a rule?
That's true, Michael, I don't know the answer to those questions. Okay,
so anyway no there you need שנה לאו הכתוב לעכב. shanah lav
hakasuv lehakev. That's when it's a detail about a ritual to assume
whether it's מעכב. me'akev. Here it's a לאו lav לא תאכל. lo
teachail. So we didn't sort of say the same thing about a
לאו. lav. Say that again? When you have a detail like you
have to do זריקת הדם zerikas hadam this way or something like
that, then you say you need it to repeat it to tell
you it's מעכב. me'akev. Here you're not talking about a detail of
the ritual and whether the ritual's valid. Here you're talking about a
prohibition to do something in a certain way כליל תהיה לא תאכל.
kalil tihyeh lo teachail. So there you don't have this... what you're...
I think what you're referring to is more about the details of
the rituals. Here it's a specific negative prohibition. Okay, so כהן שאכל
מן האימורים מהו? kohen she-achal min ha-imurin mahu? What's the law? לאו
דזרות, Lav de-zarus, when it comes to the prohibition of being a
זר, zar, a non-כהן, kohen, right? So it's basically a non-כהן kohen
is כל זר לא יאכל קדש. kol zar lo yochal kodesh. It
says any foreigner cannot eat the holy things. לא קמיבעיא לי. Lo
kamibaya li. That I don't even have to ask that question because
that's obvious that you transgress. Why? Because although you are a כהן
kohen but vis-a-vis stuff that's burned on the מזבח mizbeach you're still
a זר. zar. You are foreign. to it. You have no right
to be eating stuff on the מזבח. Mizbeach. So you certainly transgress
the prohibition of a foreigner כל זר לא יאכל קדש kol zar
lo yochal kodesh of a foreigner eating the sanctified. So you've transgressed
that and you've transgressed מעילה Meila although the גמרא Gemara isn't mentioning
מעילה, Meila, תוספות Tosafot says that's implied or whatever going it not
being addressed. כי קמיבעיא לי Ki kamibaya li what's my question? לאו
דכליל תהיה Lav d'chalil tihyeh is there a general לאו lav of
it shall be fully burnt לא תאכל? lo teiachel? Okay, do we
learn out from that פסוק pasuk that anything that should be fully
burnt should not be eaten? So מאי mai what's the story? אמר
רב ארון, Amar Rav Aron, it's interesting how many רב ארוןs Rav
Aron do you have in ש"ס? Shas? So and this is a
talking about someone talking about the עבודה Avodah too. Oh that's a
good point. אמר רב ארון לרבינא, Amar Rav Aron l'Ravina, תא שמע
ta shema come in here דתניא d'tanya רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer
omer כל שהוא בכליל תהיה kol shehu b'chalil tihyeh ליתן לא תעשה
על אכילתו liten lo taaseh al achilato that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says anything that's under the prohibition of כליל תהיה, chalil tihyeh, not
under the prohibition, under the ruling of כליל תהיה, chalil tihyeh, anything
that is supposed to be burnt, you transgress by eating it. So
if you eat stuff that's supposed to be burnt on the מזבח,
Mizbeach, maybe you transgress מעילה, Meila, תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion,
you transgress זרות, zarut, although תוספות Tosafot says another discussion is it
so obvious you transgress זרות zarut because other גמרות Gemaras make it
sound that you only transgress זרות zarut on something that a כהן
Kohen is allowed to eat as opposed to this גמרא's Gemara assumption
that since even a כהן Kohen is not allowed to eat it,
even a כהן Kohen is considered a זר. zar. So wait לאו
דכליל תהיה lav d'chalil tihyeh and as well, no תוספות Tosafot still
says it means clearly לאו דכליל תהיה lav d'chalil tihyeh means certainly
you transgress, you just have to reconcile it with other גמרות Gemaras
that sound like that's not true. You know, but okay, you can
see the תוספות Tosafot for that. And the third issue is, but
certainly what we learn from here is anything that should be burnt
on the מזבח, Mizbeach, you transgress לא תאכל, lo teiachel, it's not
just limited to a מנחה. mincha. So with all of this you
do have the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רב אלעזר,
Rav Elazar, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that you treat a מנחת חוטא
minchat chotei different from a what do you call it, different from
a מנחת נדבה minchat nedava of a כהן. Kohen. That here you
do a קמיצה, kemitza, what do you do with the rest? Do
you burn it or do you destroy it, burn it on the
floor, that is the debate between רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and his
son. Okay, let's do the next משנה, mishna, I think we can
complete this at the bottom of the page. מנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן
משיח ומנחת נסכים למזבח. Minchat Kohanim u'minchat Kohen Mashiach u'minchat nesachim l'mizbeach.
So we had before talked about things that you do a קמיצה.
kemitza. Here are things that are fully burnt. A מנחה mincha of
a כהן Kohen and the מנחה mincha of a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol חביתין, chavitin, so those are things we were just talking about,
and the מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim, the מנחה mincha that comes with
a free will sacrifice. You bring a מנחה mincha and you bring
wine and those both get fully burnt on the מזבח. Mizbeach. So
those are fully for the מזבח Mizbeach ואין בהם לכהנים, v'ein bahem
l'kohanim, כהנים Kohanim get nothing. ובזה יפה כח מזבח מכח כהנים. U'vaze
yafe koach mizbeach mikoach kohanim. And in this case, the מזבח Mizbeach
gets a lot more than the כהנים. Kohanim. I mean this is
pretty obvious and the גמרא Gemara is going to say why it
had to say it. But okay, these are categories of things that
the מזבח Mizbeach gets everything and כהנים Kohanim get nothing. Okay, now
and in contrast, שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים, Shtei halechem v'lechem hapanim, the
two loaves of שבועות Shavuot and the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim of
every Shabbos on the שולחן shulchan נאכלים לכהנים, ne'echalim l'kohanim, the כהנים
Kohanim eat them ואין בהם למזבח. v'ein bahem l'mizbeach. The מזבח Mizbeach
gets nothing. Why? Because for the שתי הלחם shtei halechem it gets
the blood of the lambs that come with it, the שני כבשי
עצרת, shenei kivshei atzeret, but it doesn't get any of the bread
itself, it can't because it's חמץ chametz and you can't put any
חמץ chametz on the מזבח. Mizbeach. And by the לחם הפנים lechem
hapanim it gets the לבונה levona that's on the שולחן shulchan but
none of the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim itself. So here it gets
none of the actual bread itself and it all goes to the
כהנים. Kohanim. ובזה יפה כח הכהנים מכח המזבח U'vaze yafe koach hakohanim
mikoach hamizbeach and here the כהנים Kohanim get everything and the מזבח
Mizbeach gets nothing. Okay, so here's cases as we started with קומץ,
kometz, some to the מזבח, Mizbeach, some to the כהנים Kohanim and
these are two categories, one is all to the מזבח Mizbeach and
the last is all to the כהנים. Kohanim. That is an interesting
way that they say that יפה כח. yafe koach. I know, it's
like the struggle here. Right, exactly, like they're competing. So let's actually
see also what the גמרא Gemara does with it. ותו ליכא? V'tu
leika? Is there no other thing that the מזבח Mizbeach gets everything?
Now והאיכא עולה? v'ha'ika olah? How about an עולה? olah? Now of
course it's a little strange because maybe we're just talking in the
context of מנחות. menachot. We're not talking about all of קרבנות. korbanot.
But okay, the גמרא Gemara thinks that because it says ובזה, u'vaze,
it's maybe trying to say this is the one time where מזבח
Mizbeach gets everything and כהנים Kohanim get nothing, meaning out of all
קרבנות. korbanot. ובזה, U'vaze, I know, but that's how the גמרא Gemara
is reading ובזה, u'vaze, this is the one time. So what about
עולה? olah? Gemara says איכא עור לכהנים. ika or l'kohanim. No, it's
not all to the מזבח, Mizbeach, the כהנים Kohanim get the skin.
והאיכא עולת העוף? V'ha'ika olat ha'of? How about a bird עולה olah
where it all goes on the מזבח? Mizbeach? No, איכא מוראה ונוצה.
ika mor'ah v'notzah. You have the crop and the like feathers or
whatever which you cut out and you throw by the side of
the מזבח. Mizbeach. Okay, so the כהנים Kohanim don't get it but
it doesn't all get burnt. So it's not exactly the same, it
doesn't all get burnt. והאיכא נסכים? V'ha'ika nesachim? How about the wine
that comes with the קרבנות, korbanot, that goes all on the מזבח?
Mizbeach? לשיתין. L'shitin. That goes to the sort of caverns and that
does not get burned on the מזבח. Mizbeach. You pour it on
a, you know, on the horn at the top of the מזבח
Mizbeach and there's a funnel and it takes it to like a,
you know, a hollow inside of the מזבח Mizbeach or caverns underneath
the ground but it does not get on the מזבח Mizbeach burned
on the מזבח Mizbeach itself, so it's not exactly the same. לשיתין
אזלי. L'shitin azli. So the Gemara says ומאי בזה? U'mai baze? So
then why is it emphasizing you know these are the only cases?
It's seemingly coming to you say don't think about something else might
be true. לאפוקי מדשמואל. L'afukei mi'd'Shmuel. Funny that a משנה Mishna is
excluding שמואל, Shmuel, but okay, maybe this idea was around before שמואל.
Shmuel. דאמר שמואל המנדב יין, D'amar Shmuel ha-minadev yayin, if you donate
wine, not wine for the נסכים, nesachim, wine for the מנחת נסכים
Minchas Nesachim we know gets poured in the funnels, but somebody just
donates wine to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, makes it like a קרבן, korban,
what do you do with it? מביא ומזלפו גבי אישים. Meivi u-mezalfo
gavye ishim. So the general opinion is you treat it like the
wine of the נסכים nesachim and you pour it down the funnels,
but שמואל Shmuel says no, if I've donated wine to the altar,
what do I do with it? I sprinkle it directly on the
fire. So according to שמואל, Shmuel, that would be an example of
something that gets fully on the fire and it is not as
well as a מנחה mincha of a כהן. Kohen. Another example of
something that is fully on the fire. So therefore it says that
קמשמע לן דלשיתין אזלי, Kamashma lan d'le-shitin azlei, it's not true, only
these things go fully on the fire, nothing else, no wine, nothing
else, this is the only things that go fully on the fire.
Now תוספות Tosfos says: what do you mean? There are other things
you can give. If you donate לבונה, levona, that gets fully burnt;
if you donate wood, that gets fully burnt. But תוספות Tosfos says:
ah, but there there was no possibility for the כהנים Kohanim to
get part of it because it's not edible, so we're only talking
about edible things. So within that context, the only these things in
the משנה Mishna are the only things that are fully on the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, nothing else. Everything else, maybe it's maybe it doesn't get
eaten by the כהנים, Kohanim, it gets poured down the שיתין, shitin,
but nothing else is fully on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Wait, so the
specific רישא reisha is excluding שמואל Shmuel and where does שמואל Shmuel
get his opinion then? Well, as תוספות Tosfos points out in the
גמרא Gemara and in another גמרא Gemara where שמואל Shmuel says it,
that he's totally contradicted by a million other sources anyway, and it's
not explicit in the משנה, Mishna, it's only inferred, so that would
not have been a slam dunk. Okay, and then the גמרא Gemara
says, and now that we've sort of contradicted one שמואל, Shmuel, מסייע
ליה לשמואל, Misayei lei l'Shmuel, but this משנה Mishna also supports another
position, a different position of שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר שמואל המנדב שמן קומצו
ושיריו נאכלין. D'amar Shmuel ha-minadev shemen komtzo ve-shiyaro ne'echalin. Here's another food,
what do you do if you've donated oil to the מזבח? mizbe'ach?
Do you burn it all on the מזבח mizbe'ach straight? That would
not sit with our משנה. Mishna. Our משנה's Mishna being read not
to be limiting to the context of מנחות, menachos, which it could
have been, as we see our משנה's Mishna being read by the
גמרא Gemara to say for all things, only the מנחות menachos of
a כהן Kohen is fully burnt, nothing else in the world of
קרבנות. korbanos. So that would support the other position of שמואל, Shmuel,
that if you donate oil, right, שמואל Shmuel says you do a
קמיצה kmitza on the oil. How do you do קמיצה kmitza on
oil? You know, yeah, you get it in your hand, maybe you
wait to get a little bit a little bit congealed or something.
Okay, and you burn it, and the כהנים Kohanim eat the rest.
You treat it like a מנחה. mincha. So that is supportive by
our משנה Mishna because if it was if the הלכה halacha was
that you burn the oil fully, then our משנה Mishna would not
have said just these מנחות menachos are fully burnt, there would have
been something else that would have been fully burnt. Again, assuming our
משנה Mishna is talking about, you know, in the context of all
קרבנות, korbanos, not just in the context of מנחות. menachos. It's also
quite fascinating this whole idea, I mean we've seen it before, here
it's just referred to in passing, that you can give things for
the מזבח mizbe'ach that are not mentioned in the תורה, Torah, right?
You read the תורה Torah you think like these are your choices,
you know, you can't go ahead and like ad-lib and say oh
I'm going to give a קרבן korban of שמן. shemen. I mean
you can donate something, but not to give it as a קרבן.
korban. And what makes it I think even more strange is it's
one thing to say
okay I'm going
to just give it as a straight קרבן korban and burn it
all, but now that I can take oil and treat it like
a quasi מנחה mincha and do a קמיצה kmitza on it, I
mean the whole idea is very bizarre, but the גמרא Gemara wants
to say this, you know, at least here it's trying to find
support for that position in our משנה. Mishna. Okay, שתי הלחם ולחם
הפנים. Shtei Ha-Lechem ve-Lechem Ha-Panim. Now the שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים Shtei
Ha-Lechem ve-Lechem Ha-Panim are the things that are fully for the כהנים
Kohanim and not for any part go on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So
ומאי באלו? U-mai bazu? Are these the only things? Again, assuming we're
not just talking about מנחות, menachos, are these the only things? והאיכא,
Ve-ha-ika, how about חטאת העוף, Chatas Ha-Of, the bird חטאת Chatas that
the כהנים Kohanim eat it fully? Right, no part, none of the
there's no אימורים eimurim by birds that get burnt, so the כהנים
Kohanim eat it fully. So אמר איכא דמא, Amar ika dama, the
blood gets put on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, at least a piece of
it, even if it's a trivial amount, the blood gets put. והאיכא
לוג שמן של מצורע, Ve-ha-ika log shemen shel metzora, how about the
לוג log of the מצורע metzora that the כהנים Kohanim eat all
the oil? Nevertheless, איכא מתנותיו, ika matnosav, you still have to sprinkle
from that whole thing seven times towards the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim,
so even though it's a trivial amount, it's not the full amount.
Well, they also put שמן shemen on the ear, right, whatever, so
the full amount does not go to the כהן Kohen as opposed
to the שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים, Shtei Ha-Lechem ve-Lechem Ha-Panim, the entire
amount goes to the כהן. Kohen. Okay, ומאי באלו? U-mai bazu? So
what's the חידוש? chiddush? These are the ones that are fully to
the כהנים, Kohanim, what else would I have thought? לאפוקי ממאן דאמר
שתי הלחם הבאות בפני עצמן לשריפה אזלן. L'afukei mi-man d'amar Shtei Ha-Lechem
haba'os bifnei atzman li-sreifa azlan. Because there's an opinion that says if
for some reason you can't bring the שתי כבשי עצרת, Shtei Kavsei
Atzeres, the lambs that are supposed to be the שלמים shelamim that
come with the שתי הלחם, Shtei Ha-Lechem, what do you do? Because
that's actually a fascinating question. Here you have שתי הלחם, Shtei Ha-Lechem,
they're חמץ, chametz, there's no way you can put them on the
מזבח mizbe'ach themselves. Let's say you don't have the lambs that come
with them. The lambs are the way in which you bring them
to the מזבח mizbe'ach is you put from the blood of the
lambs on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, which makes them okay. Let's say you
don't have the lambs, what do you do? So there's an opinion
that says okay, you sort of bring them to the מקדש Mikdash
and then you burn them because there was no way to actually,
you know, offer them as it were. So this is telling you
it's not that way. קמשמע לן דבזו יפה כח כהנים לעולם. Kamashma
lan d'bazu yafeh ko'ach kohanim l'olam. Since it says this way the
כהנים Kohanim always get, it's reading it as saying although again it
doesn't say always, you could still have read the משנה Mishna to
mean in a standard case, but that's the way the גמרא's Gemara
reading it. The כהנים Kohanim always get the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem
fully, even if there are no lambs, you're going to bring the
שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem they'll get it, which is a quite again
a bizarre idea. How are you offering the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem
if there's nothing to do with them? But in a way maybe,
you know, somewhat similar to it without the lambs? Well, might do
תנופה, Tenufa, I don't remember, but anyway, but where's the הקרבה? Hakrava?
In a way though it is somewhat similar to ביכורים. Bikkurim. Remember
ביכורים Bikkurim is the other קרבן Korban where the תורה Torah says
you know, כי כל שאר וכל דבש לא תקטירו ממנו אשה לה'
קרבן ראשית תקריבו אותם לה' ואל המזבח לא יעלו לריח ניחוח, Ki
kol se'or v'chol devash lo taktiru mimenu isheh l'Hashem korban reishit takrivu
otam l'Hashem v'el hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu l'rei'ach nicho'ach, right that you know
ביכורים Bikkurim is also like דבש, Devash, it's honey, it has dates
and whatnot. What do you do with ביכורים Bikkurim as a הקרבה?
Hakrava? You just wave it, you say some declaration, nothing goes on
the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, and that's considered a type of a הקרבה. Hakrava.
So it is interesting that possibility by the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem
without the lambs and that's how we are reading our משנה Mishna
to include even that case. Okay, let's just read, we have actually
two or three more minutes, let's just read the next משנה. Mishna.
כל המנחות הנעשות בכלי טעונות שלוש מתנות. Kol haminchot hana'asot b'kli te'unot
shalosh matanot. Every מנחה Mincha that is made in a vessel, we'll
see what's that excluding, is it every מנחה Mincha made in a
vessel? But anyway, you have three applications of שמן, Shemen, שלוש מתנות
שמן. Shalosh matanot shemen. יציקה, Yetzika, now it's going to basically say
them in reverse order for whatever reason. Okay, so the pouring, like
the drizzling maybe if you want to say, actually that's not what
יציקה Yetzika is, it's like an anointing. ובלילה, U'velila, mixing with oil.
ומתן שמן בכלי קודם לעשייתן, U'matan shemen bakli kodem la'asiyatan, and sort
of putting the oil in it before you make it, right, sounds
like a recipe, right? You know, smear the pan with a little
oil, you mix it up and then afterwards you drizzle oil on
top of it. Okay, but whatever reason it's in the reverse order.
Okay, חלות, Challos, now what about the חלות Challos which is talking
here about the מנחה Mincha of the מחבת Machavat and מרחשת? Marcheshet?
I know we normally don't think about the frying pan and the
deep pan, but the תורה Torah refers to them as חלות. Challos.
Can you give me the חומש Chumash there? Right, the תורה Torah
says by the מחבת Machavat and מרחשת. Marcheshet. Now that I'm learning
מנחות, Menachot, when I sing Shabbos זמירות Zemiros I'm paying more attention,
it says מנחה על המחבת. Mincha al hamachavat. So anyway, it says
there, right, by the מחבת Machavat and the מרחשת. Marcheshet. Actually there
it does not say חלות, Challos, it says מנחת מחבת קרבן, Minchat
machavat korban, it says מצות תהיה, Matzot tihyeh, מרחשת. Marcheshet. Yeah, actually
it doesn't say חלות Challos here. Anyway, but רש"י Rashi assumes, sorry
I take that back, but רש"י Rashi assumes that this חלות Challos
here is referring to מחבת Machavat and מרחשת. Marcheshet. So בוללן, Bolelan,
you mix them with oil, דברי רבי. Divrei Rabbi. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim
omrim, so again this we'll see more this in the גמרא. Gemara.
רש"י Rashi says what this means is that after you've baked them
and you've made them, then you are once again going to break
them up after they are now hardened and baked and mix them
again with oil. וחכמים אומרים סולת. Vachachamim omrim solet. No, you mix
them with oil when they are flour, but not after they are
baked. So that we'll see, that's a discussion about what do you
do after they're baked. We'll get back to that later. החלות טעונות
בלילה. Hachallos te'unot belila. Now now the חלות Challos of this is
talking about the מאפה תנור. Ma'afeh tanur. Remember when it says that
if you bring a מאפה תנור Ma'afeh tanur baked in an oven,
oven, it says חלות מצות בלולות בשמן ורקיקי מצות משוחים בשמן. Challos
matzot belulot bashemen urkikei matzot meshuchim bashemen. You either bring חלות Challos
or wafers, two types of things that you bake in an oven.
So what are the difference, how do you treat the חלות Challos
and the wafers different when it comes to the oil? So החלות
טעונות בלילה Hachallos te'unot belila והרקיקין משיחה. V'harkikin meshicha. So the difference
is that the חלות Challos you mix with oil and the רקיקין,
Rekikin, the wafers, you anoint with oil. כיצד מושחן, Keitzad moshchan, how
do you anoint them? כמין כי, K'min chi, like a Greek chi,
which is an X. Okay, so you make what, chi? Is that
even how you pronounce it? Is that right? Is it chi? Kai?
Kai. Okay, thank you. Kai. So you make an X on it,
you anoint it with an X. והשאר נאכלים לכהנים. V'hash'ar ne'echalin l'kohanim.
And after the remnant is eaten to the כהנים, Kohanim, of course
we know the remnant is eaten to the כהנים Kohanim after you
do the קמיצה. Kemitza. So this is a very dense and you
know little whatever משנה Mishna because it's what is all these things
that it's variously describing? How exactly do you do that? Which מנחה
Mincha is it referring to? All of this to be seen tomorrow.
Okay.